talking with docs released a video a
ways back on OIC the touted miracle
weight loss drug and if berberin could
be a replacement for OIC if you want to
lose weight in the video that they
released I was a little puzzled by some
of their claims because looking at the
scientific literature I think that they
may have gotten a few things incorrect
so I'd like to take a few moments and
dive into the berberin literature and if
it could act as a natural OIC including
covering the mechanisms the clinical
evidence and even offer some other
things that could act as a natural OIC
if you aren't familiar with talking with
docs it's a popular YouTube channel
hosted by two board certified physicians
Dr zazzel and Dr weening Who explain
different medical questions in fun easy
to understand language if you're aren't
familiar with berberin in brief it's an
herbal extract that's been around for
hundreds of years but has recently
gotten more attention for its multiple
claimed health benefits including weight
loss on the other hand OIC is a drug
that's been established to produce
significant weight loss so how do they
stack up well let's start things off by
listening to their take before we
discuss further so what are the claims
what are they taking help I mean they
call it Nature's OIC right because of
weight loss it can cause weight loss so
everyone's saying oh you can lose weight
with this it can help your cardiac
health can help your PCOS symptoms can
lower your cholesterol anti-inflammatory
benefits all these amazing things I'm
going to start taking it right away it
really is amazing okay okay so how does
it work okay first of all it's not
Nature's OIC because OIC and burin have
completely different mechanisms of
action right now we don't fully
understand Bin's mechanism of action but
we do understand oic's mechanism of
action and OIC binds to The
glp1 receptors and your
giving you the feeling that you're full
even when you're not full after eating
your stomach's distended is it sends out
a hormone that makes you feel like your
stomach's distended so you eat less it
has a ton of side effects associated
with it we've talked about it before in
another video with someone who knows
what they're talking about with OIC okay
so we talked about oics mechanism of
action and berberin acts completely
differently it's more like a metformin
action where it activates the amp K
enzyme pathway not to get too uh
complicated but it sort of helps uh the
role of insulin in your body helps your
body to stop being so insulin resistant
and that's sort of we thought to be the
mechanism there so they're completely
different mechanisms of action so it's
not Nature's OIC even though everyone's
still going to call it that for a long
time because OIC just man the last three
months it's gone crazy they start things
off by immediately dismissing bourin as
Natures of zic and they're actually
absolutely correct the mechanisms of
action are entirely different however
does that necessarily mean that it can't
produce the same results well we'll get
into that first yes berberin is believed
to work through an enzyme called ampk
which is not the case foric berberin
however does not bind ampk directly but
rather it affects other areas of the
cell directly like mitochondria which
then activate ampk this is uh important
because ampk is heavily involved in the
mechanisms like autophagy increasing
insulin sensitivity and more there's
much more biology there but we have too
much to get to OIC however is a slightly
altered version of a naturally occurring
protein in our body called glp1 gp1 when
it binds your intestines it stimulates
them to send a nervous system signal to
your pancreas to release more insulin in
addition it can bind the pancreas
directly and force it to release more
insulin however from a weight loss
perspective it actually binds your brain
cell and increases the feeling of
satiety again so much more to get into
there I have detailed videos breaking
down all of that if you're interested
anyway the point is yes they're
different but you probably care if
berbin from a results perspective is as
effective as these powerful glp1 drugs
well let's discuss is there any good
scientific evidence to support its role
in weight loss so I would say in defense
of the poor research cuz there is almost
none to be very honest with you most of
the studies that have shown that bourbon
has benefit are very small studies short
follow-up studies and poorly run studies
and we've taught our viewers in many
different videos on how to assess the
quality of a research paper or a
research project okay we'll continue in
a minute but I've also taught on how to
assess study quality which is why I
offer a short course on the matter
beyond that though they mentioned
there's almost no evidence bourin has a
weight loss effect and then they go on
to discuss that the studies are poor
quality okay this is where I was a
little baffled because I disagree
somewhat first there's definitely
evidence of Bin's weight loss effects in
fact there are several studies looking
at berberin and weight loss so I would
not say that there's almost no evidence
however the layer is what is the quality
of that research the three main
critiques levied are one very small
studies two two short studies and three
poorly run studies again here I have to
somewhat disagree I will say most
studies done on herbs and less
drug-based research tends to be
published in lower tier journals by
smaller research groups that have less
funding overall that isn't a conspiracy
it's just a fact that pharmaceutical
companies can afford to throw Millions
at a single study and big herb ain't got
that kind of pull so
we do have to rely on studies that
aren't published in major journals like
I don't know the New England Journal of
Medicine which has published on OIC like
drugs so then what evidence exists well
there are some randomized control trials
including many participants like this
one in this study the researchers
recruited over 600 participants across
three groups and did show that bourbon
reduced body weight indices for a
randomized trial that's a pretty big
sample size unfortunately it was not
Placebo controlled which weakens the
study interpretation to the point of Dr
weaning however it isn't the only one
other studies like this which did use a
placebo group and even compared against
the drug metformin which they mentioned
indicated bourin led to a weight loss
compared to Placebo there was no
difference between the burin and
Metformin conditions so if we go through
the critiques one small studies
no doubt these studies are smaller than
most drug studies but there's good
reason for that and if we constantly
dismiss interventions like bbin merely
on that fact then we'll be dismissing
all possible helpful interventions due
to weaknesses of the studies not because
the actual substances like berberin
don't actually work so I can see the
argument from both sides I'd also add
that many other molecules and
interventions are heralded as working
although although they too had few
people in the studies think like torine
or glycine as examples I'll have another
point on this in a bit number two short
studies I actually disagree here there
are many studies that last for shorter
durations than many berberin studies the
berberin studies lasted around 3 to four
months and that might not seem like a
very long time but we're talking about
weight loss which is a pretty quick
thing to experience unlike something
like I don't know cancer risk or heart
attack occurrence where three months is
woefully short three poorly run studies
there's some truth to that some studies
aren't the highest quality in the berber
and literature but uh there are others
that are double blind Placebo controlled
and randomized that indicate an effect
then as a final point before moving on
in this meta analysis on berberin the
researchers indicate there's no weight
loss effect of berberet and yet there is
a change in waist circumference which
gives a better detail on fat loss and
body composition changes also the stud's
looking strictly at Weight Loss were
fewer than those looking at waste
circumference which could contribute to
why waste circumference was shown to
improve with berberin but weight loss
did not so overall I do not agree that
we have almost no evidence I do not
agree on the point about short study
duration for an outcome like weight loss
but I do agree that we need more and
better studies uh from an application
perspective the evidence slightly leans
in favor of berberin having some form of
body composition effect although I'd
like to see much more data published to
be sure however I don't think that
there's a doubt that OIC and other glp1
drugs are much more effective and
consistently so as most berberin trials
even though they might show in effect in
some cases are limited to people with
polycystic OV syndrome metabolic
syndrome and so on glp1 drugs work
almost universally with large effects
unlike burin at least with the evidence
that we have now so I also agree with
the overall statement that bourand is
not Nature's OIC however as promised
we'll discuss a few things that could be
Nature's OIC in a minute also if you
find Value in this kind of work I have a
research review that includes videos
podcasts written suies with actionable
takeaways and much more on all kinds of
heal topics it's called the physionic
Insiders and in it I've covered other
content on burin as well including
dosing strategies if you're interested
it's linked in the description for you
to check out I hope to see you as an
Insider so these two docs also discuss
three things that could act as true
natural OIC are they true so glucose we
obviously can't tell people just to eat
glucose but if you eat complex
carbohydrates like potatoes and sweet
potatoes that some people say oh don't
ever eat any carbohydrates complex carbs
actually release glucose very slowly
along the entire length of your
intestine there are receptors there that
glp will be released from so that's the
first thing second thing peptides and
amino acids so proteins these other
macronutrients cause gp1 to go up and
cause you to feel full maybe this is
actually why people that are on heavy
duty keto and carnivore DS actually feel
better and lose weight and the last one
is short chain-free fatty acid so we're
not going to tell people to eat diets
high in fat necessarily but
interestingly fiber when it is consumed
in a healthy diet there are bacteria in
your gut fermentable bacteria that break
down the fiber into short uh fatty acids
that cause glp1 and this is one reason
why you feel full so there's ways to
hack your own glp1 like we discussed
earlier burber's mechanism of action is
not like OIC but there are nutrients
that do stimulate glp1 as mentioned
technically gluc otherwise known as
sugar or carbohydrate does stimulate
glp1 release but consuming sugar isn't
the best uh for health nor does it have
much of a satiating effect on its own so
slower digesting carbohydrates like
complex carbohydrates think quinoa oats
lentils and so on can be more filling
and one mechanism is an increase in glp1
through these carbohydrates now in
addition protein if you refer to the
same review that I just posted also
stimulates glp1 release and we know that
protein is a strong satiety nutrient
sources like fish chicken lentils black
beans and so on finally as mentioned
short chain fats which can be stimulated
in production by something like dietary
fiber seems to have a good amount of
preclinical data indicating it raises
glp1 levels there's also some Fiber
studies in humans that indicate an
increase in gp1 but admittedly there are
very few and they provide mixed results
so while fiber is beneficial in other
ways there's some uncertainty on the gp1
angle at least for now Okay so we've
covered a lot although I generally think
that we just scratch the surface here
because there's so much more but what
are the takeaways here well one berberin
is not Nature's OIC because although it
might provide some benefit on body
composition the effect is almost without
a doubt smaller than OIC like drugs not
to mention that the mechanism of action
is entirely different number two there
are true glp1 stimulators like complex
carbohydrates and protein for example so
if the mechanisms of gp1 is important to
you switching out foods for ones focused
on those would do the trick again likely
not to the level of a literal injection
of glp1 but that's probably not a
surprise I'd like focus more on satiety
as a whole rather than the glp1
mechanism if it were me but both will
accomplish that
too three the docs did a great job I do
slightly disagree on how the evidence is
portrayed but I overall agree with their
main points again so much more to be
said but if you're interested in more on
this check out this video right here
thanks for tuning in and I'll speak with
you over there
[Music]